Meadow Rise Clifton Road Netherseal Derbyshire DE12 8BP

# Philip George Whiffin $B_{Big}M_{Sc}C_{Big}MBA_{(Dist)}MIEE$

# Personal Information

Marital status: Married

Nationality: British

D.O.B.: 6/1/69

Place of Birth: United Kingdom

# **Summary**

A strong and experienced Manager and Leader whose success is built on the following three pillars:

- Leadership. Excellent track record of building, motivating and leading diverse teams, both co-located and geographically dispersed.
- Technical Knowledge. A wide base of transferable technical knowledge and skill, applicable to a wide base of technologies.
   Two technical degrees (B<sub>Eng</sub>/M<sub>Sc</sub>) and a long track record leading technology projects and problem solving.
- 3. Business Acumen. Wide business skills from identification of market opportunities, building business cases, business models, management of change, relationship management, strategy identification, implementation and business processes. Leading and influencing technical strategy within Jaguar Land Rover and the wider Ford organisation. Warwick MBA with distinction.

Recognised as a successful change agent, identifying issues and building consensus to introduce improvements. Experienced in organisational change, process change, strategy change and personnel. A strong project manager of many diverse programmes.

Worked at all stages in the product cycle from research projects through to launch management, with involvement in all the key disciplines.

Strong interpersonal and communication skills that have been adapted to many diverse situations and needs, though working with different cultures across the world. Experienced at building solid business relationships with diverse groups.

Highly rated in his current organisation. Brought in to DeltaRail to deliver real change in the way the business operates, already the recipient of recognition awards for the impact this has had.

The only UK "Ford" employee to be selected and sponsored for both of the UK Ford flagship masters degrees.

A motivated and focussed individual who always puts the team first to deliver successfully. Demonstrates high personal integrity.

Winner TATA European innovation award and Jaguar Land Rover technology award.

**Education** 

2003-2006

Warwick Business School

#### **Master of Business Administration**

- Distinction awarded.
- Sponsored by Jaguar Cars Ltd. Ford Trustmark "Flagship" degree.
   Only Ford employee to be sponsored for both MBA and MSC below.
- Part time study.
- Extensive thesis regarding the right technology strategy for the Jaguar brand was also awarded distinction and delivered to Ford Vice president.

1997-2000

Loughborough University

#### **Master of Science - Automotive Systems Engineering**

- Coverage of all technical aspects of automotive systems.
- Course objective is to allow students to successfully manage any area within automotive design/engineering/manufacture. However, technology and skills applicable to wider business environment.
- Part time study / sponsored by Jaguar Cars Ltd. "Flagship" technical degree within Ford.

1987-1990

University of Warwick

### **Bachelor of Engineering - Electronic Engineering**

- 2.
- Full time study.
- Sponsored by the British Broadcasting Corporation.

-1987

Queen Elizabeth School Atherstone

#### A Levels and O Levels

- 4 A levels: Maths, Physics, Electronics and General Studies (AABC)
- 13 O-Levels (5 grade As, 5 grade Bs and 3 grade Cs).
- 2 schools awards: Deveroux price for electronics and the school prize for Enthusiasm and Initiative in creating a school radio station.

# Professional Experience

2013-Current

Delta Rail

Derby

### **Head of Systems Engineering**

- Senior position, brought in to deliver robust Systems Engineering and process excellence to the whole business.
- Measure current state and improve, utilizing best practice.
- Strong influencing and negotiation skills needed to get buy-in and drive change.
- Internal communication and education strategies.
- Includes evaluation and generation of new business opportunities.
- Improving the business, bidding, research, design, safety, quality, test, build and validation processes.
- Managing Safety, Quality and RAMS teams associated with largest delivery project., bringing new technology into the sector.
- Business involved in signaling control, traffic management, automatic routing, decision support and other rail systems.
- Already seen as a successful change agent having a positive impact

2011-2013 Jaguar Land Rover

Coventry

## **Advanced Systems Engineering Manager**

- Responsible for systems engineering of all Jaguar Land Rover Advanced / Research projects.
- Responsible for developing, piloting and rolling-out Systems engineering process to deliver real business benefit for the wider business and to advanced engineering.
- Part of the whole-company systems engineering governance team.
- Developing the innovation process.
- Piloting systems engineering techniques at vehicle level on major projects.
- Worked with Tata TBEM Business Excellence Model and team, particularly regarding innovation.
- Leading Plug-In Hybrid Introduction from a whole vehicle perspective.
- Part of the core team leading the corporate strategy investigations into addressing the "megacity" vehicle market, matching user needs to technology (electrification / power train, infotainment, vehicle experience).

2008-2011 Jaguar Land Rover

Coventry

#### **Hybrid Systems Engineering Manager**

- Responsible for systems engineering of all Jaguar Land Rover Hybrid Projects within the newly formed Hybrid centre of Competence.
- Leadership in an area critical to the future of JLR's business
- Particularly tasked with bringing delivery experience to this area and ensuring these complex integration projects are delivered robustly.
- Developing Robust Systems Engineering process and Tools (Doors), where no process existed.
- Building the team and expertise.
- Managing the hybrid functional safety team (ISO26262), responsible for hybrid systems safety cases.
- Managing the Hybrid integration team, responsible for prototype design, vehicle/rig/test-cell commissioning, hardware in the loop testing, software integration and serial communications.
- On steering teams to deliver systems engineering, requirements management and ISO26262 across the company.

2007-2008 Jaguar Land Rover

Coventry

## **Stop-Start Manager**

- Responsible for delivering the Freelander 2 Stop-Start system in record time – from initial concept to production. This was a business critical project for the brand.
- Led from initial demonstrator prototype through to and including launch.
- Built up a small/focussed task force for delivery.

- Delivered with quality "built in" i.e. used quality/systems processes to ensure failure mode avoidance, this was one of the most successful projects at JLR from any quality metric point of view.
- Worked closely with manufacturing to ensure smooth transition of new technology into the plant – we actually improved the right first time and first time through metrics whilst introducing new technology.
- We won the Tata innovation award, Jaguar Land Rover Technology award and were runners up in the IET innovation and transport awards for this project.
- Developed functional safety approach across Ford, Volvo and Jaguar Land Rover for analysis of these systems, including innovative ways of meeting functional safety needs whilst delivering customer benefits.

2005-2007 Jaguar Land Rover Coventry

## Sustainability / Hybrid Projects Manager

- Responsible for all Jaguar Land Rover Sustainable Technology Projects.
- Foundation member of the Sustainability team at JLR.
- Leadership of an area critical to the future of JLR's business.
- Responsible for:
  - 1. Hybrid strategy within JLR based on business needs / environment.
  - 2. Integration of this strategy within the wider Ford global strategy and representation of JLR at Ford global hybrid summits.
  - 3. Selection of the correct technology / partners.
  - Building the business case / logic presenting this to the Ford board.
  - Building the hybrid team. Identification / recruitment of key skills.
     Resource sharing within Ford. Including building the modeling expertise which became fundamental to our strategy development.
  - Securing outside funding from DTI/Energy saving trust for research.
- Successfully influenced and changed the Ford global hybrid strategy

   as a small group we batted well above our level.

2001-2005 Jaguar Land Rover Coventry

# **Advanced Projects Manager**

- Working within the Jaguar Land Rover Advanced Engineering/Research Department delivering advanced technology projects through to implementation readiness.
- Selection of appropriate projects / due diligence / building of a business case for project approval.
- Building delivery teams, identifying skills, recruiting etc.
  - Often asked to take on "under performing" staff to motivate and focus them.
- Ensuring smooth handover of projects to vehicle programmes capturing requirements / building relationships.
- Budget Management. Management of large budgets to ensure project delivery on-time and within-budget. Creation of credible spend profiles.

- Overall project management of a portfolio of projects.
- Drove changes to the technology selection and delivery process changes implemented globally.
  - Research projects always represent a risk, so it is also important to terminate them quickly were the technology is not right so as not to waste resource.
  - Clear and simple project metrics to allow global comparisons to ensure most appropriate use of funds. Based on "lean" principals.
  - Single process now in place worldwide across Ford, Volvo and Mazda.
- Technical leadership of projects including H.M.I., steer by wire, advanced chassis systems, safety systems etc.
- Also asked to take over leadership of failing projects, all of which were successfully "turned around" and delivered.
- Leadership for safety critical projects and functional safety processes, initially using IEC61508 and DEF-Stan as best practice and then ISO26262. Delivering hazard analysis, safety integrity ratings and safety case/arguments.
- Built Functional Safety into the research delivery process.

1999-2001 Jaguar Land Rover Liverpool

## Launch Manager

- Responsible for all Electrical related Launch issues on the Jaguar Xtype:
  - 1. Leadership / recruitment of the electrical launch team to be relocated to Halewood.
  - 2. Issue investigation and solution. Essential to deliver a robust solution in a very short time frame as high build volumes increase the profit loss per hour.
  - 3. Liaison with suppliers and core engineering to deliver most efficient solutions.
  - 4. Developing/implementing training plans for ex-Ford staff to build/rectify electrical issues on Jaguar X-types.

1997-1999 Jaguar Cars Ltd Coventry

# Principal Engineer - Engine Management Systems

- Departmental Manager for Engine Management Systems.
- Management of a largest department within Electrical.
- Responsible for delivery of EMS systems to vehicle projects, emissions compliance, diagnostics, development of future strategies, building long term partnerships with suppliers, developing staff etc.
- This proved to be an excellent grounding for management and leadership as many of the experienced staff (whose support was needed for success) were also candidates for the role.

#### **Engineer / Senior Engineer / Project Engineer**

- Taken on as part of the graduate scheme in 1990. First step was a year long programme covering all aspects of the business.
- Based in electrical engineering, working on many electrical/electronic systems.
  - Led Development of new transmission controller.
  - Led first implementation of OBDII onto transmission control systems.
  - Very early on given responsibilities critical to the company when representing Jaguar to CARB.
  - Led engine management component team (sensors / actuators).

1988-1990

British Broadcasting Corporation

London

#### **Sponsored Student**

Sponsored through University by BBC Transmission Engineering.

# Additional professional activities

Also Involved in: Key Words

- Six sigma projects (quality).
- Tata Business Excellence Model.
- Lean process deployment teams.
- Departmental re-organisations / managing change.
- Recruitment/selection.
- Value Management / Value Mapping.
- Project Management.
- Functional Safety (ISO26262 / IEC61508 / EN 50128 / CSM).
- Systems Engineering.
- Strategy development.
- Government Funding.
- Environmental Technologies
- Process change/introduction.
- Railway Control Systems
- Automotive Systems

# Professional memberships

Member of the IET.

# Community activities

Led Neighbourhood Engineer activities at local schools to raise awareness of the opportunities within the engineering profession.

#### **Objective**

Continually looking to improve and stretch myself in roles that will exercise management and technical skills.

# Interests and activities

Mountain biking, road cycling, running, badminton and swimming are the main sports I enjoy.

Completed the London Brighton and Birmingham Oxford cycle rides for charity. I have also completed the coast to coast off-road route and the Pennine cycleway from Derby to Berwick. I am also a member of Burton upon Trent Cycling club.

I have completed the 3 peaks challenge (Snowdon, Scafell and Ben Nevis) within 24 hours, and a parachute jump for charity.

I regularly compete in the Jaguar Challenge / Jagtrek event and our team best is third place with a first in the events category.

I am also a keen motorcyclist, I am a qualified advanced rider and observer – training others. I also organise many trips both bike touring and to motorsport venues.

## **Key words**

EGAS, ISO26262, IEC61508, ISO15288, ISO12207, INCOSE, Powertain control, Value, System-V, QFD, FMEA, Safety case., Strategy, Technology Selection, Management of Change, Robust Process, Sustainability, EN50128, IEC 15288, Signalling, Railway Control, Traffic Management.

# Other Information

Very computer literate, with skills in Word, Excel, Project, Visio, Matlab, Simulink, Caliber, Doors, INCA to name a few.